Inventory of the Kenneth R. Hansen Papers, 1948-1982
Hoover Institution Archives
Inventory of the Kenneth R. Hansen Papers, 1948-1982
93056
Hansen, Kenneth R. (Kenneth Rudolph), 1923-1981.
57 manuscript boxes (23.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
The papers contain speeches and writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, and printed matter related to the economic development of developing countries, technology transfer to developing countries, and American trade with and investment in developing countries. Some materials relate to American foreign trade and foreign aid policy during the presidential administrations of John F. Kennedy and Lyndon B. Johnson.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1993.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Related Materials
Annelise Graebner Anderson papers, Hoover Institution Archives
J. Burke Knapp papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Asia Foundation records, Hoover Institution Archives
Joel Bernstein papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Records of the Office of Management and Budget (Record Group 51), United States National Archives
Biographical/Historical Note
An American economist, Kenneth R. Hansen was assistant director of the Bureau of the Budget and a consultant for development projects in the Middle East and Southeast Asia. Hansen was born in St. Anthony, Idaho, on June 1, 1923. He began his government work in the Military Intelligence Service at the start of World War II and served as an executive officer of that group from 1946 to 1949. From 1948 to 1949, Hansen was the chief of economic intelligence for the United States Allied Commission for Austria (USACA). Hansen was a special assistant for the Economic Cooperation Authority mission as chief to Austria under the Marshall Plan, where he dealt with problems of trade and payments, including East-West trade and currency reforms. From 1952 to 1954, he worked in the Mutual Security Agency negotiating efforts to control East-West trade and forming economic policy for the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO). In 1958, Hansen led a group of international sociologists and economists preparing a seven-year development plan for Iran. He returned to the U.S. in 1961, when he became assistant director of the Bureau of the Budget. He left that position in 1964.
After Hansen resigned from government service, he served as the vice president for corporate planning of Syntax Corporation from 1964 to 1968. After 1968, he became a consulting economist for various organizations that implemented projects in developing countries. Hansen became president of the American and Canadian operations of the urban planning organization Doxiadis Associates in 1971. Returning to California, Hansen consulted for organizations in Iran, Turkey, Sudan, Bangladesh, and other countries, as well as heading a team of Harvard University faculty advising the government of Singapore on transportation. He served as an economic consultant for a variety of organizations, including the World Bank and Dames & Moore, as well as serving as a senior advisor to the Sinai, Egypt Development Program and the Volvo Lahore Transportation Project. Hansen passed away in 1981 in Los Altos Hills, California.
Source:
Kenneth R. Hansen obituary. New York Times. 31 August 1981
Scope and Content of Collection
The bulk of the collection relates to Kenneth R. Hansen's consulting work, including reports and correspondence concerning various projects in the Middle East and Southeast Asia. Many of these project reports were either written by Hansen or shaped and influenced by him. Hansen was concerned with issues such as economic development, mass transportation, urban studies, improving human settlements, agriculture, technology transfer, and delivery of medicines and medical technology. He often worked on projects for multiple companies in the same region. Although the majority of the material dates from after Hansen resigned as assistant director in the Bureau of the Budget, some of his correspondence from that time period can be found where noted, such as in box 3. For documents related to the Bureau of the Budget, see materials dated from 1961 to 1964, when Hansen was employed by that organization. For a detailed list of Hansen's consulting activities and professional career, see his curriculum vitae in box 2.
Hansen was involved in several studies of Iran, including serving as the field director of the Harvard Economic Advisory Group to Iran. His correspondence with Edward S. Mason, director of that group, can be found in boxes 2, 20, 47 and 56. In 1975, Hansen was an advisor to the Center for Spatial Planning of the Plan & Budget Organization of the Iranian government, where he helped to develop the National Spatial Strategy Plan. This study proposed spatial planning policies to deal with the demographic and social changes caused by rapid economic growth in Iran. In 1976, Hansen consulted on a project for AB Volvo in Sweden, which produced studies on urban transportation in Shiraz and Isfahan.
In addition to that project, Hansen worked with AB Volvo on the Volvo Lahore Transportation Project, which aimed to provide a comprehensive urban transport system to the 4.5 million residents of Lahore, Pakistan, and provided 300 Volvo buses for use. Reports from this project can be found throughout the collection, including in box 36 and box 57.
In 1976, Hansen became a consultant for Dames & Moore, working on multiple projects for the corporation, including the Sinai, Egypt Development Program, where he served as a senior advisor. The Camp David Accords, which Egypt and Israel signed in 1978, led to the signing of a peace treaty between the two countries in 1979. One result of this treaty was that the Sinai Peninsula was returned to Egypt, which led to a development focus in that area. The study aimed to provide a development strategy concerning areas such as water resources, usable resources, agricultural and fishery activities, industrial location, population, and tourism. Materials from this project can be found where indicated throughout the collection.
Hansen served as the advisor to the Secretary General for the Habitat: United Nations Conference on Human Settlements, which was held in 1976 in Vancouver. The main outcome of this conference was the establishment of UN-HABITAT, a United Nations program with the goal of providing adequate shelter for all people. Materials for this conference can be found in box 5, box 25, and where indicated.
Hansen served as an advisor to the government of Singapore, where he was the head of a project to advise the government on urban transportation alternatives, including the evaluation of an underground heavy rail system. The Singapore Mass Transit Study was managed in accordance with a project document agreed upon by the Singapore government and the United Nations Development Programme (with the International Bank for Reconstruction and Development acting as its executing agency). Phase I of the study began in 1972 and examined five alternative public transport systems, concluding that a rail mass transit system was the best option. The second phase of the study, which began in 1975, had the goal of providing an examination of the technical and financial feasibility of such a system. In 1980, the Mass Rapid Transit (MRT) Review Team, a group of Harvard University specialists led by Hansen, published a report titled "Singapore's Transport and Urban Development Options," which suggested that an all-bus transit system might be preferable to a rail system. In 1981, the MRT Review Team assisted the Singapore MRT Authority in the Comprehensive Traffic Study (CTS), which determined that an all-bus system would be inadequate to serve Singapore's transportation needs. Materials concerning both the Singapore Mass Transit Study and the Comprehensive Traffic Study can be found throughout the collection under the heading "Singapore mass rapid transit studies."
In addition to his consulting work, Hansen also gave lectures for various colleges, conferences, and groups, including the National War College, the World Affairs Council, the Committee on Foreign Relations, and the Executive Seminar Centers at New York and Berkeley, California. As a senior fellow at the Adlai Stevenson Institute, he lectured at eleven universities. He spoke at Stanford in 1968 and 1969 as part of the Special Seminar Program and lectured at the University of California, Berkeley Graduate School of Business from 1968 to 1971. Some of his lectures for Berkeley can be found in box 25. Hansen's lecture materials can be found in the files of the "speeches and writings by Hansen" throughout the collection. His speeches and writings can also be found among his conference and seminar materials, such as in box 47.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
United States. Bureau of the Budget.; Economic assistance, American.; East-West trade.; Technology transfer.; Investments, American--Developing countries.; Economic development.; United States--Commerce.; United States--Economic policy--1961-1971; Developing countries.; Economists.
Collection Contents
- Speeches and writings by Hansen, 1957-1968 (Folder 1)
  Includes notes, seminar information, and "Economic Warfare" speech
- Correspondence (Folder 1)
  - Harvard, 1968-1970 (Folder 1)
  - Mohgadam, Reza, 1965-1966 (Folder 1)
  - Syntex, summer project (David N. Daniels), 1961-1968 (Folder 1)
- Report to President Kennedy on Supersonic Transport Program, 1963 (Folder 1)
- Bureau of the Budget, Hansen resignation press release, 1964 (Folder 1)
- Iran and Singapore reports, 1960-1980 (Folder 1)
- Clippings on East-West trade, U.S. economic policy and budget, Iran crisis, and inflation, 1954-1978 (Folder 1)
- Curriculum vitae and resume, 1974 (Folder 2)
- Speeches and writings by Hansen, 1957-1977 (Folder 2)
  Includes "Economic Warfare," National War College speech
- Iran correspondence and reports (Folder 2)
  - General, 1970-1973 (Folder 2)
  - Asia Development Corp., 1974 (Folder 2)
  - Tehran Development Council, 1973 (Folder 2)
- Correspondence (Folder 2)
  - General, 1978-1980 (Folder 2)
  - Mason, Edward, regarding East-West trade, 1960 (Folder 2)
- U.S. Government committee prints, 1957-1974 (Folder 2)
- Iran Plan & Budget Organization, National Spatial Strategy Plan, proposed work program by Hansen, 1976 (Folder 3)
- Speeches and writings by Hansen, 1955-1967 (Folder 3)
  Includes lecture "Economic Sanctions"
- Correspondence (Folder 3)
  - General, 1948-1971 (Folder 3)
  - Bureau of the Budget, 1961-1962 (Folder 3)
  - Iran, 1969-1971 (Folder 3)
    Includes William R. Polk materials
- Awards, undated (Folder 3)
- Clippings, 1953-1970 (Folder 3)
- Conference and seminar materials, 1966-1979 (Folder 3)
- Biographical file (Folder 4)
  - Reserve Officers' Training Corps (ROTC) papers, 1964 (Folder 4)
  - Photographs of Hansen, undated (Folder 4)
  - Clippings, 1964-1968 (Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1966-1982 (Folder 4)
- Speeches and writings by Hansen, 1955-1971 (Folder 4)
- Singapore mass rapid transit studies, correspondence, 1980 (Folder 4)
- "Transport Planning for Tehran" report, 1974 (Folder 4)
- Printed matter, 1978 (Folder 4)
- Reports (Folder 5)
  - Stanford Medical Center, 1979 (Folder 5)
  - Development reports, 1970-1979 (Folder 5)
  - Habitat: United Nations Conference on Human Settlements, 1976 (Folder 5)
  - Tehran Airport study, 1973 (Folder 5)
- ALZA Corporation, memorandum, undated (Folder 5)
- Reports (Folder 6)
  - General, 1968-1982 (Folder 6)
  - Egypt, 1972-1977 (Folder 6)
  - Iran national spatial planning report, undated (Folder 6)
- Sinai, Egypt Development Program, Dames & Moore, memoranda and request for proposals, 1978-1979 (Folder 6)
- Reports (Folder 7)
  - General, 1977-1979 (Folder 7)
  - Sinai, Egypt Development Program, Dames & Moore, 1979 (Folder 7)
  - Habitat: United Nations Conference on Human Settlements, circa 1976 (Folder 7)
  - Iran Plan & Budget Organization, National Spatial Strategy Plan, 1975 (Folder 7)
- Philippines development project, correspondence and proposal, undated (Folder 7)
- Discussion papers, Gustav F. Papanek, 1979 (Folder 7)
- Iran Reports (Folder 8)
  - General, 1975-1978 (Folder 8)
  - Volvo, undated (Folder 8)
  - Tehran Development Council, 1976-1977 (Folder 8)
- Sinai, Egypt Development Program, Dames & Moore, technical proposal, 1979 (Folder 8)
- Doxaidis report, Existics (Urban Planning), 1972 (Folder 9)
- Sinai, Egypt Development Program, Dames & Moore, 1981 (Folder 9)
- Iran trip for Crocker Bank report, 1978 (Folder 9)
- Consultant brochures, undated (Folder 9)
- Volvo materials, undated (Folder 9)
- Transport reports and grant proposals, 1974-1980 (Folder 9)
- Stanford University Hospital, meeting materials, 1979-1981 (Folder 10)
- Conference materials, 1966-1973 (Folder 10)
- Printed matter, Helliniki Techniki, undated (Folder 10)
- Agency for International Development, statements and reports, 1978 (Folder 11)
- International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (World Bank), East Pakistan report, 1978 (Folder 11)
- Dames & Moore, Philippines proposal, 1979 (Folder 11)
- Printed material, health care, 1972 (Folder 11)
- Sinai, Egypt Development Program, Dames & Moore, contract, 1980 (Folder 12)
- Consultant list, Bank Group, 1973 (Folder 12)
- William R. Polk working paper, 1970 (Folder 12)
- "The Future of Human Settlements," paper by Constantinos Doxiadis for the Nobel Symposium, 1969 (Folder 12)
- United Nations conference, tourism report, 1971 (Folder 12)
- Printed matter and reports, including on tourism, 1977-1980 (Folder 12)
- Conference on Pharmaceuticals for Developing Countries, draft proceedings, 1979 (Folder 13)
- Harvard Business Review, Ray Vernon, 1980 (Folder 13)
- Printed matter and reports, 1971-1975 (Folder 13)
- Reports (Folder 14)
  - General, 1967-1973 (Folder 14)
    Includes reports from Adlai Stevenson Institute
  - Dames & Moore, Engineering proposal, 1978 (Folder 14)
  - Pharmaceuticals and developing countries report, 1979 (Folder 14)
  - Transportation reports, 1971 (Folder 14)
- Reports (Folder 15)
  - General reports and printed matter, 1974-1978 (Folder 15)
  - Urban development reports, 1966-1967, undated (Folder 15)
  - Vancouver proposed goals, 1973-1974 (Folder 15)
- Stanford University Medical Center, memoranda, 1979 (Folder 15)
- Asia Development Corporation, company information, 1975 (Folder 15)
- Doxaidis Association termination agreement, 1972 (Folder 16)
- Reports (Folder 16)
  - Appropriate Technology in Residential Construction, 1972 (Folder 16)
  - Housing Finance and Employment in Latin America, June 1972 (Folder 16)
  - Bay Area Regional Organization research project, July 1968 (Folder 16)
  - Harvard program of Technology and Society, circa June 1972 (Folder 16)
  - Brazil Investment Program, 1972-1974 (Folder 16)
  - Tourism in the Pacific Rim, Hudson Institute, March 1972 (Folder 16)
  - Rhode Island Public Transit Authority, 1968 (Folder 16)
  - International Industrialization Institute, Special International Panel (Folder 16)
- Iran reports (Folder 17)
  - Iran Plan & Budget Organization, National Spatial Strategy Plan, 1976 (Folder 17)
  - Volvo transportation reports, 1976-1977 (Folder 17)
- Volvo, Iran transportation report, 1977 (Folder 18)
- Saudi Arabia (Folder 18)
  - Bechtel Corporation industrial development proposal, 1974 (Folder 18)
  - Industrial structure and growth prospects report, 1973 (Folder 18)
- Reports and printed materials, 1978-1981 (Folder 18)
- Dames & Moore (Folder 18)
  - Meeting summary, 1979 (Folder 18)
  - Company information, 1978-1979 (Folder 18)
  - Saudi Arabia report, 1976 (Folder 18)
- Pharmaceuticals in developing countries report, 1979 (Folder 18)
- Engineering Foundation Conference, brief, 1976 (Folder 18)
- Reports (Folder 19)
  - International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (World Bank), Iran economic development report, 1974 (Folder 19)
  - Reports on buses, 1978-1979 (Folder 19)
  - Iran reports, 1975-1977 (Folder 19)
    Includes report to Tehran Development Council
  - Indonesia reports, 1973-1974 (Folder 19)
- Dames & Moore (Folder 19)
  - Company information, undated (Folder 19)
  - Printed matter, 1976 (Folder 19)
- ALZA Corporation (Folder 19)
  - Annual report, 1975 (Folder 19)
  - Printed matter and press releases, undated (Folder 19)
  - Iran drug research proposal, 1976 (Folder 19)
- Correspondence and memoranda, 1971-1980 (Folder 19)
- Clippings, 1975-1976, undated (Folder 19)
- Genesys Systems, 1977 (Folder 19)
- Volvo letter to head of Plan and Budget Organization of Iran, 1977 (Folder 19)
- Correspondence (Folder 20)
  - Consulting, 1973-1980 (Folder 20)
  - Mason, Edward (Harvard Economic Advisory Group to Iran), 1958-1959 (Folder 20)
- Inter-American Development Bank, correspondence and reports, 1973-1974 (Folder 20)
- Iran reports (Folder 20)
  - Dames & Moore, Tehran, Iran development report, 1978 (Folder 20)
  - Iran Plan & Budget Organization, National Spatial Strategy Plan, 1976 (Folder 20)
  - Tehran Development Council Secretariat, 1978 (Folder 20)
  - "Prospective Long-Range Planning in Iran,", 1977 (Folder 20)
    Report of Hansen to Mohammad Yeganeh of Iran Plan and Budget Organization
  - DeKalb Agricultural Research, development of seed activities report, undated (Folder 20)
- Iran reports and correspondence (Folder 21)
  - ALZA Corporation, 1975 (Folder 21)
  - Crocker National Bank, 1975-1976 (Folder 21)
  - International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (World Bank), 1973 (Folder 21)
  - Asia Development Corporation, 1974 (Folder 21)
  - Bechtel Corporation, 1969-1970 (Folder 21)
- Reports (Folder 21)
  - International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (World Bank), 1974 (Folder 21)
  - Saudi Arabia, 1974 (Folder 21)
  - Singapore mass rapid transit studies, 1977-1981 (Folder 21)
- Speeches and writings by Hansen, 1978 (Folder 22)
  Includes notes, drafts and reports on Iran
- Iran reports and correspondence (Folder 22)
  - Prospective Long-Range Planning in Iran, 1977 (Folder 22)
  - Tehran Development Council Secretariat, 1977 (Folder 22)
- Volvo correspondence, reports, notes, 1976-1980 (Folder 22)
- Saudi Arabia project, research and notes, 1974-1975 (Folder 22)
- International Bank for Reconstruction and Development (World Bank), Suez Canal Zone Reconstruction Program, memoranda, 1974 (Folder 22)
- Indonesia report, 1979 (Folder 22)
- Fellowship agreement for the Adlai Stevenson Institute, 1971 (Folder 22)
- Crocker International Bank, correspondence, 1977 (Folder 22)
- Clippings, 1964-1967 (Folder 22)
- Asia Development Corporation, 1973-1974 (Folder 22)
- Reports (Folder 23)
  - General, 1971, undated (Folder 23)
  - Adlai Stevenson Institute reports by Hansen and others, 1973-1974 (Folder 23)
  - Iran, 1974-1978 (Folder 23)
  - World Bank, Philippines, 1979 (Folder 23)
- Genesys, reports and notes, 1979 (Folder 23)
- Dames & Moore, correspondence, memoranda, and meeting minutes, 1977-1980 (Folder 23)
  Includes Special Markets Management Team files
- Dames & Moore, correspondence and memoranda, 1977-1981 (Folder 24)
  Includes Sinai, Egypt Development Program
- Volvo, correspondence and reports, 1981, undated (Folder 24)
  Includes Hansen's report on turnkey projects
- Sudan reports, correspondence, notes, meeting minutes, 1968-1969 (Folder 24)
- DeKalb Agricultural Research, Middle East report and memoranda, 1974-1975 (Folder 24)
- Crocker National Bank, correspondence, 1977 (Folder 24)
- ALZA Corporation, correspondence and reports, 1975-1977 (Folder 24)
- Reports (Folder 25)
  - Brazil, 1972 (Folder 25)
  - Nicaragua, 1979 (Folder 25)
  - Agency for International Development, 1978 (Folder 25)
  - Habitat: United Nations Conference on Human Settlements, preparatory reports, 1975 (Folder 25)
- ALZA Corporation, correspondence and reports, 1975-1976 (Folder 25)
- Delos Nine Symposium, undated (Folder 25)
- Printed matter (Folder 25)
  - General, 1947-1972 (Folder 25)
  - Committee prints, 1966-1973 (Folder 25)
  - University of Chicago Round Table, 1968 (Folder 25)
    Includes dialogue by Hansen
- Course outlines for UC Berkeley School of Business Administration, 1967-1971 (Folder 25)
  Includes lecture outlines by Hansen
- Correspondence and reports (Folder 26)
  - Agency for International Development Health Strategy Study, 1978 (Folder 26)
  - ALZA Corporation, 1971-1972 (Folder 26)
  - Adlai Stevenson Institute, 1970-1973 (Folder 26)
  - Doxiadis Associates, 1970-1972 (Folder 26)
- Hansen announcements list and press release, 1971 (Folder 26)
- Speeches and writings by Hansen, drafts, 1971, undated (Folder 26)
- Asia Foundation, proposal by Hansen, 1971 (Folder 26)
- Speaker appraisal forms for Hansen, 1975 (Folder 26)
- Reports (Folder 27)
  - Habitat: United Nations Conference on Human Settlements, correspondence and preparatory reports, 1974-1975 (Folder 27)
  - Delos Symposium, 1963-1971 (Folder 27)
  - Development reports by Hansen and others, 1971-1980 (Folder 27)
  - Inter-American Development Bank, road transport report, 1974 (Folder 27)
  - Bureau of the Budget, planning report, 1963 (Folder 27)
- Correspondence, 1971-1972 (Folder 27)
- Speeches and writings by Hansen, 1966, undated (Folder 27)
  - International Business and Foreign Policy: Ours and Theirs, undated (Folder 27)
  - Lecture, "Effect of Political Climates on International Business,", 1966 (Folder 27)
  - Asia - Five New Thresholds of Change," World Affairs Council, 1967 (Folder 27)
  - "East-West Trade: Dilemma or Delusion?", 1967 (Folder 27)
  - Transcript of meeting, Adlai Stevenson Institute, 1973 (Folder 27)
- Correspondence and reports (Folder 28)
  - Development Bank Project, Adlai Stevenson Institute, 1974-1975 (Folder 28)
  - "Prospective Long-Range Planning in Iran,", 1977 (Folder 28)
  - Volvo, Lahore Transportation Project, 1979-1981 (Folder 28)
    Includes notes
- Dames & Moore, correspondence and employment applications, 1977-1980 (Folder 28)
- Speeches and writings by Hansen (Folder 28)
  Includes correspondence and conference materials
  - General, 1967, undated (Folder 28)
  - "Personnel Requirements for New Institutions," Second Conference, America and the World, Georgetown University School of Foreign Service, 1964 (Folder 28)
  - "Interpenetration of Foreign and Domestic Policies," Seminar on International Operations, Civil Service Commission and Foreign Service Institute, 1963 (Folder 28)
  - Panel discussion at the Society for International Development Annual Meeting, 1964 (Folder 28)
  - Civil Service Commission Executive Seminar Center speech, 1963 (Folder 28)
- Singapore mass rapid transit studies, report by Hansen, 1980 (Folder 28)
- Reports (Folder 29)
  - Reports on development banks, 1968-1980 (Folder 29)
    Includes Development Bank Project, Adlai Stevenson Institute, 1975
  - Technology and Science in World Bank Activities, 1975 (Folder 29)